Guide to the Granite-BiMetallic Consolidated Mining Company Records 1884-1919
Montana State University-Bozeman Library
Granite-BiMetallic Consolidated Mining Company Records
1884-1919
Montana State University Library, Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections P.O. Box 173320 Bozeman, MT 59717-3320 United States Phone (406) 994-4242 Fax (406) 994-2851 http://www.lib.montana.edu/archives/ University Archivist spcoll@www.lib.montana.edu
Collection 2140, MtBC, us
Granite-BiMetallic Consolidated Mining Company
.8 linear feet
The Granite-BiMetallic Consolidated Mining Company Records consists of records from the Granite Mountain Mining Company followed by records of the Granite-BiMetallic Consolidated Mining Company and some materials of T. H. Kleinschmidt, a mine investor. The papers include copy ledger books; letter and account copy files; a time book; expense bills and receipts from suppliers and shippers; survey information; records of smelting, shipping and purchases of the mined ores; leases, bids, agreements and stockholder communications and some miscellaneous post cards and pay check stubs.
Historical Note
The Granite-BiMetallic Consolidated Mining Company of Philipsburg, Montana, was formed in April 1898 by the merger of the Granite Mountain Mining Company and the Bi-Metallic Mining Company. In 1881, Charles D. McLure with several St. Louis capitalists, including Charles Clark, Augustus B. Ewing, Lewis M. Rumsey, Moses Rumsey, and Charles Taussig formed a syndicate incorporated as the Granite Mountain Mining Company. In June 1886, another property was incorporated as the Bi-Metallic Mining Company by a syndicate comprised of many of the same owners of the Granite Mountain Mining Company, with the addition of Paul A. Fusz and others. Following the 1898 merger of the two syndicates, the company had several years of profitable operation. After it went into receivership in 1903, the mines were operated primarily on the lease system. They produced sporadically through the 1920s, and in 1934 the Granite-BiMetallic Consolidated Mining Company was dissolved.
The collection consists of records from the Granite Mountain Mining Company followed by records of the Granite-BiMetallic Consolidated Mining Company and some materials of T. H. Kleinschmidt, a mine investor. The papers include copy ledger books; letter and account copy files; a time book; expense bills and receipts from suppliers and shippers; survey information; records of smelting, shipping and purchases of the mined ores; leases, bids, agreements and stockholder communications and some miscellaneous post cards and pay check stubs.
This collection is open for research.
Collection 2140 was received from the Museum of the Rockies in 1985 with other business paper collections and had no individual accession number. In 1970, Marjorie Durand of Phillipsburg, Montana donated accession 886, a group of Granite Mountain Mining Company papers which has been combined with the 2140 collection. Additional materials, arranged as folders 6-12 in Box 2, were donated by Darlene Mills of Lolo, Montana on March 16, 2015.
Kleinschmidt, Theodore H. (Theodore Henry), 1839-1913
Granite Mountain Mining Company
Mines and mineral resources-Montana-Granite County; Mining corporations-Missouri-Saint Louis
Business records
Mines and Mineral Resources; Montana
- Butte area expense ledger pages, 1886-1896 (Box-folder 1/1)
  (fragile)
- Photocopies of Butte area expense ledger pages, 1886-1896 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Letter file book- Granite Mountain Mining Company, December 1884-October 1885 (Box-folder 1/3)
- Weekly time sheet book - Granite Mountain Mining Company, September 1886 (Box-folder 1/4)
- Expense bills from Northern Pacific Railroad Company shipping, 1888; 1890 (Box-folder 1/5)
- Granite Mountain Mining Company - assorted bills and receipts, 1885-1891 (Box-folder 1/6)
- Survey detail sheets - Granite Mountain Mining Company, undated (Box-folder 1/7)
- Pay check copies - Granite Mountain Mining Company, 1889 (Box-folder 1/8)
- Post card telegrams - Granite Mountain Mining Company, circa 1880s (Box-folder 1/9)
- Bullion sheets - Granite Mountain Mining Company, 1887-1902 (Box-folder 1/10)
- Assorted papers- leases, bids, agreements - Granite Mountain Mining Company, 1889-1892 (Box-folder 1/11)
- Copy account book- Granite Bi-Metallic Consolidated Mining Company, 1905-1906 (Box-folder 1/12)
- Purchase records - Garfield Smelter Company from Granite Bi-Metallic Consolidated Mining Company, 1908 (Box-folder 2/1)
- Leaser and Company shipments - Granite Bi-Metallic Consolidated Mining Company, 1913-1914 (Box-folder 2/2)
- Special stockholder meeting papers - Granite Bi-Metallic Consolidated Mining Company, 1917 (Box-folder 2/3)
- Smelting records - Granite Bi-Metallic Consolidated Mining Company, 1908; 1918-1919 (Box-folder 2/4)
- Kleinschmidt mining papers, 1898-1905 (Box-folder 2/5)
- Board minutes, 1903 (Box-folder 2/6)
- Board minutes, 1904 (Box-folder 2/7)
- Board minutes, 1905 (Box-folder 2/8)
- Board minutes, 1906 (Box-folder 2/9)
- Miscellaneous correspondence (Box-folder 2/10)
- Miscellaneous reports (Box-folder 2/11)
- Printed materials (Box-folder 2/12)
- Map of the Granite Mountain Mine claims and tunnels, 1887 (Cabinet Oversize)